<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<rfc
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    ipr="trust200902"
    docName="draft-mahesh-opsawg-ainetops-00"
    category="info"
    consensus="true"
    submissionType="IETF"
    tocInclude="true"
    sortRefs="true"
    symRefs="true"
    version="3">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="AI NetOps">Recommendations for AI-Driven Network Operations Work in the IETF</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-mahesh-opsawg-ainetops-00"/>
    <author fullname="Mahesh Jethanandani">
      <organization>Arrcus, Inc</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mjethanandani@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>
    <keyword>AI network operations YANG governance</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
        A growing number of individual Internet-Drafts address the use
        of Artificial Intelligence (AI) and Machine Learning (ML) in
        network operations and management.  These efforts are currently
        spread across multiple working groups and mailing lists without
        a coordinated path.  This document surveys the landscape,
        identifies where work belongs across existing and new venues
        (OPSAWG, NMOP, NETCONF WG, ONSEN WG, and BoFs approved for
        IETF 126), and provides guidance to OPS area chairs on how to
        handle adoption requests for AI-related drafts.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>

    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>
        AI and ML techniques are increasingly being applied to network
        operations: anomaly detection, closed-loop remediation, intent
        translation, and autonomous device management.  The IETF
        community has responded with a growing number of individual
        drafts exploring governance frameworks
        <xref target="I-D.smith-opsawg-ai-network-governance"/>,
        network management agent architectures
        <xref target="I-D.zhao-nmop-network-management-agent"/>,
        use cases <xref target="I-D.king-rokui-ainetops-usecases"/>,
        and research challenges
        <xref target="I-D.irtf-nmrg-ai-challenges"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        Work on AI-driven network operations should be discussed on
        the AINETOPS mailing list (ainetops@ietf.org) for general
        discussion, and brought to OPSAWG for adoption and chartering
        decisions.
      </t>
      <t>
        AI and network operations tooling is evolving rapidly.  IETF
        standardization is most valuable for work items that are
        grounded in stable operational requirements  --  audit trails,
        governance parameters, security practice  --  rather than areas
        where industry tooling is iterating faster than IETF can
        publish.  The proposed work items are chosen with that
        constraint in mind.
      </t>
      <t>
        AI agents performing network management do what human operators
        do, potentially faster and with more data ingestion.  This
        argues for reusing existing IETF protocols and data models
        rather than creating AI-specific ones, and grounds the scope
        of the proposed work.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document identifies where the IETF can make a unique and
        concrete contribution  --  specifically through YANG data models,
        protocol extensions, and operational guidance  --  and provides a
        dispatch map for OPS area chairs fielding adoption requests for
        AI-related drafts.  It also identifies areas that are better
        left to research, industry forums, or other bodies.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="current-landscape" title="Current Landscape">
      <t>
        The following efforts are relevant to AI-driven network
        operations in the IETF and IRTF:
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <xref target="I-D.smith-opsawg-ai-network-governance"/>
          proposes a governance framework of thirteen principles for
          AI-mediated autonomous network device management, covering
          human authority, safety, auditability, reversibility, and
          bounded autonomy.
        </li>
        <li>
          <xref target="I-D.zhao-nmop-network-management-agent"/>
          defines a Network Management Agent (NMA) concept, an AI-
          driven entity that bridges service intent and network
          operations using an Intent-Awareness-Analysis-Decision-
          Execution (IAADE) control loop.  The draft identifies three
          interfaces  --  Agent-to-User (A2U), Agent-to-Controller (A2C),
          and Agent-to-Network (A2N)  --  but explicitly defers the
          definition of the A2C interface to future documents.
        </li>
        <li>
          <xref target="I-D.king-rokui-ainetops-usecases"/> documents
          use cases including reactive troubleshooting, proactive
          assurance, closed-loop optimization, misconfiguration
          detection, and virtual operator assistance.
        </li>
        <li>
          <xref target="I-D.irtf-nmrg-ai-challenges"/> identifies
          research challenges for coupling AI with network management,
          including distribution of AI tasks and privacy concerns.
        </li>
        <li>
          The AINETOPS non-WG mailing list (ainetops@ietf.org) was
          established to discuss integration of AI and ML in network
          operations using IETF technologies.
        </li>
        <li>
          <xref target="I-D.zeng-opsawg-applicability-mcp-a2a"/>
          argues that NETCONF has five architectural gaps for AI-driven
          operations  --  AI semantic translation, long-lived cross-domain
          orchestration, multi-agent consensus, rapid DevOps iteration,
          and large artifact delivery  --  and proposes the Model Context
          Protocol (MCP) and Agent-to-Agent (A2A) protocol as
          complementary layers alongside NETCONF, not replacements
          for it.
        </li>
        <li>
          <xref target="I-D.zeng-opsawg-llm-netconf-gap"/> performs a
          gap analysis of NETCONF and RESTCONF for LLM-driven intent-
          based networking, identifying the absence of a YANG-to-JSON-
          Schema automation pipeline as a blocking gap: LLMs cannot
          reason over YANG tree notation but can consume JSON Schema
          tool descriptors.
        </li>
        <li>
          <xref target="I-D.zw-opsawg-mcp-network-mgmt"/> specifies
          concrete MCP extensions for network equipment management,
          defining tools that map directly onto YANG datastore
          operations (get, edit, commit, rollback) and capability
          advertisement that lets MCP servers declare their supported
          YANG modules.
        </li>
        <li>
          <xref target="I-D.irtf-nmrg-llm-nm"/> proposes a framework
          for LLM-assisted network management with a mandatory human-
          in-the-loop audit step before any AI-generated configuration
          is deployed, and defines YANG modules for both the LLM
          response record and the human approval workflow.
        </li>
        <li>
          ONSEN (Operationalizing Network and Service Abstractions) is
          a new working group being seated for the first time at
          IETF 126. ONSEN
          addresses operational abstractions for networks and services,
          with potential overlap with AI agent governance and
          operational state work.
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        Several BoFs have been approved for IETF 126 that are directly
        relevant to AI-driven network operations.  This document was
        written before these BoFs were proposed; the following are noted
        as coordination points rather than definitive routing targets,
        since not all approved BoFs are WG-forming and not all
        WG-forming BoFs will form working groups:
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          AUDIT (Agent Use of Delegation and Interaction Traceability):
          covers delegation mechanisms and interaction traceability for
          agent systems, overlapping with audit log and attribution work.
        </li>
        <li>
          CATALIST (Coordinating Agent To Agent List of efforts): covers
          A2A coordination.
        </li>
        <li>
          Agent Communication Protocols: covers inter-agent communication
          protocols, overlapping with A2A and A2C interface work.
        </li>
        <li>
          Discovery of Agents, Workloads, and Named Entities: covers
          discovery mechanisms for agent-based systems.  There is a genuine technical disagreement in the
          community about whether existing MCP tool descriptions and JSON
          Schema are sufficient for capability advertisement, or whether a
          more formal schema is needed.  This BoF is the appropriate venue
          to resolve that question.
        </li>
        <li>
          DMSC (Dynamic Multi-agent Secured Collaboration): covers
          security for multi-agent collaboration, overlapping with the
          security BCP work.
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        Collectively, these efforts have established the problem space
        and use cases.  The next step is to translate this into
        standards-track work with concrete, interoperable deliverables.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ietf-strengths" title="Where IETF Can Contribute">
      <t>
        The IETF's established strengths lie in defining YANG data
        models, protocol behavior, and operational guidelines.  Applied
        to AI-driven network operations, this means:
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          Standardizing the data models that describe how AI agents
          are configured, governed, and monitored  --  so that operators
          can manage AI agents through the same NETCONF/RESTCONF
          interfaces they already use for network devices.
        </li>
        <li>
          Extending existing management protocols to carry attribution
          metadata for AI-initiated changes, enabling interoperable
          audit trails and rollback.
        </li>
        <li>
          Producing operational security guidance as a BCP, so that
          operators deploying AI agents can follow a common baseline
          regardless of vendor implementation.
        </li>
        <li>
          Defining the information model for AI agent capabilities,
          audit trails, and operational state in YANG  --  as
          transport-agnostic schemas that implementations can consume
          via NETCONF/RESTCONF, gNMI, or other transports.  Where
          protocol extensions to NETCONF or RESTCONF are needed, that
          work belongs in the NETCONF WG, which is the home for those
          IETF-owned protocols.
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        The IETF is not well-positioned to specify AI algorithms, model
        architectures, or training methodologies.  Those topics belong
        in the IRTF or in industry forums.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="proposed-work" title="Proposed Work Items">

      <section anchor="wg-scope" title="Working Group Scope">
        <t>
          The volume of AI-related work and the burden of triaging it
          in existing WGs argues for a dedicated AIOPS working group.
          OPSAWG should serve as the interim home while the charter is
          developed with the chairs, the community, and the IESG.  The
          charter should commit to the work items described in this
          section and explicitly exclude architecture surveys, AI
          algorithm specification, and gap analyses that stand alone
          without an associated deliverable.
        </t>
        <t>
          Experimental and research work related to AI-driven network
          operations should be directed to the IRTF NMRG.  Chartered
          work items in OPSAWG or a dedicated AIOPS WG are limited to
          standards-track and BCP deliverables.
        </t>
        <t>
          The following table maps existing individual drafts to their
          proposed home for adoption purposes.  This is intended as a
          reference for chairs fielding adoption requests at IETF 126.
        </t>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Draft</th>
              <th>Proposed Action</th>
              <th>Home</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>draft-king-rokui-ainetops-usecases</td>
              <td>Adopt as use cases/requirements input</td>
              <td>OPSAWG/AIOPS</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>draft-smith-opsawg-ai-network-governance</td>
              <td>Adopt for Informational RFC</td>
              <td>OPSAWG/AIOPS</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>draft-zhao-nmop-network-management-agent</td>
              <td>Coordinate; A2C interface item to NMOP</td>
              <td>NMOP</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>draft-zeng-opsawg-applicability-mcp-a2a</td>
              <td>Informational reference; MCP BCP builds on it</td>
              <td>OPSAWG</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>draft-zw-opsawg-mcp-network-mgmt</td>
              <td>Informational reference</td>
              <td>OPSAWG</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>draft-irtf-nmrg-llm-nm</td>
              <td>IRTF track; coordinate on audit log</td>
              <td>IRTF NMRG</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <t>
          A use cases and requirements document, building on
          <xref target="I-D.king-rokui-ainetops-usecases"/>, should
          be the first adopted work item.  This document will not be
          published as an RFC but will inform the scope and priorities
          of the YANG data model work.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="yang-models" title="YANG Data Models">
        <t>
          The YANG language is used here as a formal information
          modeling tool, not as a mandate for NETCONF/RESTCONF as the
          implementation transport.  These schemas are
          transport-agnostic; implementations may expose them via
          NETCONF/RESTCONF, gNMI/gRPC, or other mechanisms appropriate
          to the deployment context.  Where protocol extensions to
          NETCONF or RESTCONF are required, that work belongs in the
          NETCONF WG.  Non-IETF transports such as gRPC, MCP, and REST
          are valid implementation choices and are out of scope for
          this charter.
        </t>

        <section anchor="capability-discovery" title="AI Agent Capability Discovery">
          <t>
            There is an active debate in the community about whether
            existing mechanisms  --  MCP tool descriptions with JSON
            Schema, skill definitions in natural language  --  are
            sufficient for AI agent capability advertisement in
            multi-vendor, multi-domain network deployments.  Those
            with hands-on experience building MCP servers and agents
            report that well-defined tool descriptions work effectively
            in practice, including for complex tasks.  Others argue
            that natural-language skill names do not scale across
            vendors without a more formal schema, since capability
            names are not unique and semantics are not verifiable.
          </t>
          <t>
            This debate is the right one for the IETF to inform, but
            it is not resolved in this document.  The Discovery of
            Agents, Workloads, and Named Entities BoF (approved for
            IETF 126) is the appropriate venue to work through whether
            and what IETF standardization is needed for agent
            capability advertisement.  Work on this topic should be
            directed there.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="audit-log-model" title="AI Agent Audit Log YANG Model">
          <t>
            <xref target="I-D.smith-opsawg-ai-network-governance"/>
            specifies in detail what an audit trail for an AI agent
            must contain: action timestamps, the anomaly that triggered
            the action, AI prompts and responses, pre- and post-action
            state snapshots, the outcome of the action, and whether
            the action was taken autonomously or required human
            approval.
          </t>
          <t>
            This is a well-defined schema.  Standardizing it as a YANG
            data model ensures that AI agent audit logs are
            interoperable across vendors and consumable by existing
            operational tooling.  Retention periods are a local policy
            decision; the model should provide a configurable retention
            parameter without mandating a default value.
          </t>
          <t>
            Current deployments frequently use OpenTelemetry with
            Prometheus or OpenMetrics for agent observability.  A YANG
            audit log model provides a normative, vendor-neutral schema
            for management systems that require a deterministic
            interface to the audit trail, complementing rather than
            replacing existing observability infrastructure.
          </t>
          <t>
            The model should also capture the human-in-the-loop
            workflow: whether a proposed action required human approval
            before execution, the identity of the approver, the
            timestamp of approval or rejection, and any operator
            annotation attached to the decision.  This extends the
            audit record beyond what the AI agent did autonomously to
            include the governance interactions that constrained it,
            enabling post-hoc analysis of where human oversight was
            exercised and where it was not.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="governance-model" title="AI Agent Configuration and Governance YANG Model">
          <t>
            This model targets the management plane controller or
            orchestrator that oversees AI agents, not the AI agent
            runtime itself.  Not all agent implementations embed a
            NETCONF/RESTCONF server; this model is intended to be
            consumed by the operator's existing NMS through the
            management interface of the orchestration layer.
          </t>
          <t>
            The governance parameters described in
            <xref target="I-D.smith-opsawg-ai-network-governance"/>  -- 
            the Action Registry, operator-managed Allow List and Block
            List, rate limit parameters (actions per hour, per-target
            limits, cooldown periods), protected resource targets, and
            degradation level thresholds  --  are all operator-configured
            state.
          </t>
          <t>
            Standardizing these as a YANG data model allows operators
            to configure and audit AI agent governance through the same
            NETCONF/RESTCONF interfaces they already use, and enables
            consistent policy enforcement across heterogeneous
            deployments.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="state-model" title="AI Agent Operational State YANG Model">
          <t>
            The runtime state of an AI agent  --  its current degradation
            level, active rate-limit counters, retry counts per target,
            escalation state, and current execution mode (autonomous
            versus monitoring-only)  --  constitutes operational state
            that operators need to observe.
          </t>
          <t>
            This model is further informed by the IAADE control loop
            defined in
            <xref target="I-D.zhao-nmop-network-management-agent"/>.
            The operational state should include the current phase of
            the IAADE loop (Intent, Awareness, Analysis, Decision, or
            Execution), the active intent being processed, and for
            each phase: the inputs consumed, the outputs produced, and
            any exceptions encountered.  This gives operators
            visibility into not only the health of the AI agent but
            also what it is currently doing and why.
          </t>
          <t>
            Standardizing this as a YANG operational state model
            allows operators to monitor AI agent health and activity
            through existing telemetry and streaming telemetry
            infrastructure, using the same tools they use to observe
            network device state.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="protocol-attribution" title="NETCONF/RESTCONF Extensions for AI Agents">
        <t>
          When an AI agent modifies device configuration via NETCONF
          or RESTCONF, its identity is already captured through the
          standard session authentication mechanisms that apply to any
          management plane user.  If additional attribution metadata  -- 
          such as a flag identifying the session as AI-initiated  --  is
          determined by the community to be warranted for NMS and SIEM
          correlation, that work belongs in the NETCONF WG, which is
          the appropriate home for extensions to IETF-owned management
          protocols.  This document does not propose specific extension
          text.
        </t>
        <t>
          Any work on NETCONF or RESTCONF extensions to support AI
          agent use cases belongs in the NETCONF WG.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="mcp-extensions" title="MCP Extensions for Network Management">
        <t>
          The Model Context Protocol (MCP) is an industry specification
          maintained by Anthropic, not an IETF standard.  IETF does
          not control its evolution.  The IETF's role is limited to
          producing operational guidance on how to use MCP effectively
          alongside IETF-defined YANG models and NETCONF/RESTCONF
          infrastructure.
        </t>
        <t>
          An informational or BCP document on MCP operational best
          practices for network management would cover: tool
          granularity guidance (favor purpose-built operational tools
          over raw protocol mappings), error code conventions, rollback
          and confirmation signaling, and capability discovery via
          ietf-yang-library exposed as an MCP tool.  The existing
          drafts <xref target="I-D.zeng-opsawg-applicability-mcp-a2a"/>
          and <xref target="I-D.zw-opsawg-mcp-network-mgmt"/> provide
          a starting point for this work.
        </t>
        <t>
          This work is suitable for OPSAWG, in coordination with any
          AI agent interoperability frameworks that emerge from
          industry forums.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="agent-interfaces" title="Agent-to-Agent and Agent-to-Controller Interfaces">
        <t>
          <xref target="I-D.zhao-nmop-network-management-agent"/>
          identifies two interfaces that require standardization in the
          independent NMA deployment mode: the Agent-to-Controller
          (A2C) interface between the NMA and an existing SDN
          controller, and  --  implicitly  --  peer Agent-to-Agent (A2A)
          interfaces for multi-agent coordination in heterogeneous
          deployments.
        </t>
        <t>
          The CATALIST BoF (Coordinating Agent To Agent List of
          efforts) and the Agent Communication Protocols BoF, both
          approved for IETF 126, address A2A and inter-agent
          communication.  If either results in a working group, that
          is the natural home for this work.  If not, NMOP is the
          fallback, subject to whether the NMOP charter accommodates
          it  --  a question to be resolved with the NMOP chairs, the WG,
          and the IESG before work is formally proposed there.
        </t>
        <t>
          The A2C interface should define how the NMA invokes
          controller capabilities (topology queries, telemetry
          subscriptions, configuration enforcement) as abstract tools,
          and how the controller returns results and exceptions to the
          NMA.  The interface should be expressed using existing IETF
          management protocols (NETCONF or RESTCONF) and YANG data
          models, avoiding the introduction of a new protocol.
        </t>
        <t>
          Beyond the single NMA-to-controller case, real deployments
          involve multiple AI agents operating concurrently across
          domains, each with different capabilities and authorities.
          <xref target="I-D.zeng-opsawg-applicability-mcp-a2a"/>
          identifies multi-agent consensus and long-lived cross-domain
          orchestration as gaps not addressed by NETCONF.
        </t>
        <t>
          The trust and authorization aspects of A2A interactions
          should be coordinated with identity work in the security
          area, including any Workload Identity Tokens (WIT) work,
          to avoid redundancy.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="encoding" title="Encoding for AI Agent Consumption">
        <t>
          YANG data returned from NETCONF/RESTCONF operations can be
          verbose in XML or JSON form, imposing significant token costs
          when consumed by LLM-based agents.  As AI agents become
          consumers of network management data, encoding efficiency is
          an operational concern alongside human readability.
        </t>
        <t>
          A BCP or informational document surveying encoding
          alternatives  --  including CBOR (RFC 8949) and selective field
          projection  --  with guidance on their trade-offs for AI agent
          use cases, would complement the YANG data model work.  This
          work is suitable for OPSAWG.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="bcp" title="Operational Security BCP">
        <t>
          The security considerations specific to AI-mediated network
          management are qualitatively different from those of
          traditional management plane access.  They include:
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>
            The AI service as an attack surface: prompt injection via
            device-generated telemetry strings included in AI prompts,
            and compromise of the AI service API endpoint.
          </li>
          <li>
            Credential management: AI agents require management plane
            credentials that must not appear in plaintext
            configuration or AI prompts.
          </li>
          <li>
            Audit trail integrity: write-ahead logging with integrity
            protection and forwarding to external aggregators to
            prevent tampering.
          </li>
          <li>
            Exfiltration risk: AI agents that send telemetry to
            external AI services may inadvertently exfiltrate
            topology, credential, or customer data.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          A BCP document addressing these considerations would give
          operators deploying AI agents a normative security baseline
          independent of vendor implementation.  This work is suitable
          for OPSAWG.  This work should be coordinated with the DMSC
          (Dynamic Multi-agent Secured Collaboration) BoF, approved
          for IETF 126, which addresses security for multi-agent
          collaboration environments.  Emerging OAuth and workload
          identity work in the security area is relevant to credential
          management for AI agents and should be referenced.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="informational" title="Governance Principles as Informational RFC">
        <t>
          The thirteen governance principles defined in
          <xref target="I-D.smith-opsawg-ai-network-governance"/> are
          well-developed and provide a sound foundation for
          implementors.  Publishing this document as an Informational
          RFC would give it stable citable status without requiring it
          to carry normative weight.  The normative content  --  the
          specific configurations and behaviors that implement these
          principles  --  is better expressed in the YANG data models
          described in <xref target="yang-models"/>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="lifecycle" title="AI Agent Lifecycle Management">
        <t>
          An AI agent operating in a network environment has a
          lifecycle beyond its initial deployment: it must be
          discoverable by operators and peer agents, its behavior must
          be verifiable against benchmarks, it may be upgraded as the
          underlying model or toolset changes, and it may be
          decommissioned or replaced.  In multi-agent systems, these
          lifecycle events must be coordinated to avoid capability gaps
          or conflicting authorities.
        </t>
        <t>
          These concerns map across several venues: discovery belongs
          with the Discovery of Agents BoF; benchmarking and
          evaluation methodology belongs in IRTF NMRG, with
          coordination with the BMWG which has existing work on AI
          benchmarking; upgrade and operational lifecycle management is
          suitable for OPSAWG/AIOPS.  This document does not propose
          specific work items for each at this stage but flags them as
          areas requiring attention in charter development.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="out-of-scope" title="Out of Scope">
      <t>
        The following are explicitly out of scope for the proposed
        IETF work:
      </t>
      <dl>
        <dt>AI network architecture documents</dt>
        <dd>
          IETF should not produce standalone AI network architecture
          survey documents.  Where a well-developed architecture
          exists  --  such as the NMA architecture in
          <xref target="I-D.zhao-nmop-network-management-agent"/>  -- 
          IETF work should produce data models and protocol extensions
          that implement it, not relitigate the architecture.  Surveys
          and taxonomies without an associated deliverable are out of
          scope.
        </dd>
        <dt>AI and ML algorithm specification</dt>
        <dd>
          Specifying which algorithms to use for anomaly detection,
          classification, or remediation recommendation is outside
          IETF scope.  The YANG data models and protocol extensions
          proposed here are intentionally AI-service-agnostic.
        </dd>
        <dt>Gap analyses and surveys without committed deliverables</dt>
        <dd>
          Gap analyses that are directly coupled to a committed
          standards-track or BCP work item within the same charter are
          in scope.  Gap analyses that stand alone  --  without an
          associated data model or protocol document  --  should not be
          chartered work items, as the use cases and requirements
          document is sufficient to scope the normative work.
        </dd>
        <dt>External framework alignment guidelines</dt>
        <dd>
          Guidelines for aligning IETF YANG data models with TMF,
          3GPP, or other external frameworks are outside IETF scope
          and should be addressed through liaison statements rather
          than chartered work items.
        </dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <section anchor="deliverables-summary" title="Summary of Proposed Deliverables">
      <t>
        The following table summarizes the proposed deliverables,
        organized by IETF-OPS-AD/AINETOPS categories.
      </t>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Category</th>
            <th>Proposed Work Item</th>
            <th>Track</th>
            <th>Home Venue</th>
            <th>Notes</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>Network Operations</td>
            <td>Use cases and requirements document</td>
            <td>Not published as RFC</td>
            <td>OPSAWG/AIOPS</td>
            <td> -- </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Network Operations</td>
            <td>AI agent audit log information model (YANG)</td>
            <td>Standards Track</td>
            <td>OPSAWG/AIOPS; coordinate with AUDIT BoF</td>
            <td> -- </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Network Operations</td>
            <td>AI agent operational state information model (YANG)</td>
            <td>Standards Track</td>
            <td>ONSEN (if in scope); else OPSAWG/AIOPS</td>
            <td> -- </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Network Operations</td>
            <td>AI agent configuration/governance information model (YANG)</td>
            <td>Informational</td>
            <td>ONSEN (if in scope); else OPSAWG/AIOPS</td>
            <td> -- </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Network Operations</td>
            <td>AI-attribution extension for NETCONF/RESTCONF (if needed)</td>
            <td>Standards Track</td>
            <td>NETCONF WG</td>
            <td>Subject to community consensus on need</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>LLM/AI Benchmarking</td>
            <td>Encoding guidance for AI agent consumption of YANG data</td>
            <td>Informational/BCP</td>
            <td>OPSAWG/AIOPS</td>
            <td> -- </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Discovery &amp; Naming</td>
            <td>AI agent capability advertisement</td>
            <td>TBD</td>
            <td>Discovery of Agents BoF (if WG forms); else OPSAWG/AIOPS</td>
            <td>Open question; see <xref target="capability-discovery"/></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Transport</td>
            <td>Agent-to-Agent (A2A) interface</td>
            <td>Standards Track</td>
            <td>CATALIST or Agent Comms BoF (if WG forms); else NMOP</td>
            <td>Contingent on BoF outcomes</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Transport</td>
            <td>Agent-to-Controller (A2C) interface</td>
            <td>Standards Track</td>
            <td>CATALIST or Agent Comms BoF (if WG forms); else NMOP</td>
            <td>Contingent on BoF outcomes</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Security</td>
            <td>Operational security BCP</td>
            <td>BCP</td>
            <td>OPSAWG/AIOPS; coordinate with DMSC BoF</td>
            <td> -- </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Security</td>
            <td>Agent identity and authorization</td>
            <td>TBD</td>
            <td>SEC WG</td>
            <td>Coordinate with OAuth/WIT work</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Observability</td>
            <td>AI agent lifecycle: discovery</td>
            <td>Informational</td>
            <td>Discovery of Agents BoF (if WG forms); else OPSAWG/AIOPS</td>
            <td> -- </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Observability</td>
            <td>AI agent lifecycle: benchmarking and evaluation</td>
            <td>Informational</td>
            <td>IRTF NMRG; coordinate with BMWG</td>
            <td> -- </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Observability</td>
            <td>AI agent lifecycle: upgrade and operational management</td>
            <td>Informational</td>
            <td>OPSAWG/AIOPS</td>
            <td> -- </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> -- </td>
            <td>AI governance principles (Smith draft)</td>
            <td>Informational</td>
            <td>OPSAWG/AIOPS</td>
            <td> -- </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> -- </td>
            <td>MCP operational best practices</td>
            <td>Informational/BCP</td>
            <td>OPSAWG/AIOPS</td>
            <td> -- </td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <t>
        Items in the Discovery &amp; Naming and Transport categories
        are contingent on BoF outcomes.  OPSAWG/AIOPS is the fallback
        home in all cases where a BoF does not produce a working group.
        Items marked for ONSEN are contingent on ONSEN's charter
        accommodating them.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="operational-considerations" title="Operational Considerations">
      <t>
        Operators deploying AI agents for network management should
        ensure that the management interfaces used by AI agents are
        subject to the same access control, logging, and change
        management policies as human operator access.  The YANG data
        models proposed in <xref target="yang-models"/> are designed
        to integrate with existing NETCONF/RESTCONF management
        infrastructure rather than requiring separate management planes
        for AI agents.
      </t>
      <t>
        Deployments using the independent NMA mode  --  where an NMA
        writes directly to device configuration alongside other
        management systems  --  introduce a multiple-writer problem.
        Operators should enforce single-writer semantics at the
        orchestration layer, either by routing all configuration
        changes through the NMA or by using NETCONF private candidates
        to isolate concurrent sessions.  Work items proposing
        independent NMA deployments should address write-conflict
        prevention explicitly in their requirements.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        The security considerations for AI-mediated network management
        are discussed in <xref target="bcp"/>.  Key concerns include
        prompt injection via device-generated data, credential
        exposure to AI services, audit trail integrity, and telemetry
        exfiltration.  These are addressed in detail in
        <xref target="I-D.smith-opsawg-ai-network-governance"/>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references anchor="references" title="References">
      <references anchor="informative-references" title="Informative References">
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.smith-opsawg-ai-network-governance.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.zhao-nmop-network-management-agent.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.king-rokui-ainetops-usecases.xml"/>
        <reference anchor="I-D.irtf-nmrg-ai-challenges" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-irtf-nmrg-ai-challenges-05">
          <front>
            <title>Research Challenges in Coupling Artificial Intelligence and Network Management</title>
            <author fullname="Jerome Francois" initials="J." surname="Francois">
              <organization>University of Luxembourg and Inria</organization>
            </author>
            <author fullname="Alexander Clemm" initials="A." surname="Clemm">
              <organization>Independent</organization>
            </author>
            <author fullname="Dimitri Papadimitriou" initials="D." surname="Papadimitriou">
              <organization>3NLab Belgium Research Center</organization>
            </author>
            <author fullname="Stenio Fernandes" initials="S." surname="Fernandes">
              <organization>Central Bank of Canada</organization>
            </author>
            <author fullname="Stefan Schneider" initials="S." surname="Schneider">
              <organization>Digital Railway (DSD) at Deutsche Bahn</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="March" year="2025"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-irtf-nmrg-ai-challenges-05"/>
        </reference>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.zeng-opsawg-applicability-mcp-a2a.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.zeng-opsawg-llm-netconf-gap.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.zw-opsawg-mcp-network-mgmt.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.irtf-nmrg-llm-nm.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>

    <section numbered="false" anchor="acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>
        The recommendations in this document were informed by
        discussions on the OPSAWG and AINETOPS mailing lists, and by
        the presentations at IETF 125.  The governance framework
        proposed in
        <xref target="I-D.smith-opsawg-ai-network-governance"/> by
        Andy Smith and Nalin Pai provided the concrete foundation from
        which the YANG data model proposals are derived.
      </t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
